<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://shaou77.github.io</id>
    <title>天地一沙鸥</title>
    <updated>2026-01-08T12:21:31.860Z</updated>
    <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://shaou77.github.io"/>
    <link rel="self" href="https://shaou77.github.io/atom.xml"/>
    <subtitle>飘飘何所似，天地一沙鸥。</subtitle>
    <logo>https://shaou77.github.io/images/avatar.png</logo>
    <icon>https://shaou77.github.io/favicon.ico</icon>
    <rights>All rights reserved 2026, 天地一沙鸥</rights>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[沙鸥（个人简历，吐槽，以及代码相关）]]></title>
        <id>https://shaou77.github.io/post/sha-ou-ge-ren-jian-li-tu-cao-yi-ji-dai-ma-xiang-guan/</id>
        <link href="https://shaou77.github.io/post/sha-ou-ge-ren-jian-li-tu-cao-yi-ji-dai-ma-xiang-guan/">
        </link>
        <updated>2026-01-08T12:14:21.000Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure data-type="image" tabindex="1"><img src="https://shaou77.github.io/post-images/1715835388432.jpg" alt="" loading="lazy"></figure>
<blockquote>
<p>orcid：<code>&lt;https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4737-7975&gt;</code>      邮箱：<code>liyd39@mail.sysu.edu.cn</code></p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="基本信息">基本信息</h2>
<h3 id="心血管内科-重症医学-2006至今">心血管内科-重症医学   (2006至今)</h3>
<p>生于80年代的苦逼内宅小医生一枚，一直在繁忙的科室工作。</p>
<p><strong>Github：</strong> <a href="https://github.com/shaou77" title="https://github.com/shaou77">github.com/shaou77</a>   |  <strong>个人博客：</strong> <a href="https://octocat.github.io">shaou77.github.io</a></p>
<h2 id="专业技能">专业技能</h2>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>心内科知识</strong>：有一点积累，心电图略懂一二，但是最新知识可能已经过时。</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>重症知识</strong>：半路出家，根基不牢，半懂不懂，呼吸和抗感染是短板。</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>编辑知识</strong>：40岁考了一个国家出版专业技术人员中级，略懂一二。但不可否认，从地级市医院到教学医院，在临床医生向研究型医生转型早期，审稿工作对于思维训练获益很大。</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>医学研究</strong>：擅长用别人的数据做自己的研究（即所谓大数据研究）。对R和回顾性研究有一点心得。在AI年代，善于复现别人的研究（就是自己没什么想法），但往往复现的研究发表不出来啊。(╯°Д°)╯︵┻━┻</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="研究经历">研究经历</h2>
<h3 id="github-httpsgithubcomshaou77">GitHub - <a href="https://github.com/shaou77/">https://github.com/shaou77/</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>本人做的基于公共数据库的大数据研究，都会放在我的GitHub上。毕竟在升级早期，站上的大神们的代码对我帮助很大，我也做一点微小的工作，把自己微小的火花传下去，只是质量不高罢了。</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="paper1-association-between-red-cell-distribution-width-and-hospital-mortality-in-patients-with-sepsis">Paper1 - Association Between Red Cell Distribution Width and Hospital Mortality in Patients with Sepsis</h3>
<ul>
<li>
<p>DOI: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/03000605211004221">10.1177/03000605211004221</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>代码地址：</strong><a href="https://github.com/shaou77/rdw-and-sepsis">https://github.com/shaou77/rdw-and-sepsis</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>第一篇SCI，从0到1的突破。只是当时心里承受能力轻，投了一两家被拒了，就投了一个大家说好发的。——结果怎么投的时候还没事，发的时候就成了预警期刊呢？你一个Sage出版社，比我年纪还大的期刊啊……晋升没用上，版面费也没报到。o(▼皿▼メ;)o</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>但是文章质量我觉得还可以。也是我首篇被引用数达两位数的文章。样本量大，传统统计方法做的很全面，亚组分析完善，甚至当时时髦的NRI，IDI都做了。只是开始不会用Rstudio的r或者rmd文件，代码都是用文本保存的，可能有一些偏差。</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>补充：现在已经不是预警了。</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="paper2-albumin-level-at-admission-to-the-intensive-care-unit-is-associated-with-prognosis-in-cardiac-arrest-patients">Paper2 - Albumin Level at Admission to the Intensive Care Unit Is Associated With Prognosis in Cardiac Arrest Patients</h3>
<ul>
<li>
<p>DOI: <a href="https://doi.org/10.7759/cureus.14501">10.7759/cureus.14501</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>代码地址</strong> ：无</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>其实是第一篇的延伸和模仿，当时也是脸皮薄，拒了几次就投了一个E-SCI，很快发了，无心插柳，晋升反而用到了。非SCI，代码也懒得维护了。</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="paper3-red-blood-cell-distribution-width-predicts-in-hospital-mortality-in-patients-with-a-primary-diagnosis-of-seizures-in-the-icu-a-retrospective-database-study">Paper3 - Red blood cell distribution width predicts in-hospital mortality in patients with a primary diagnosis of seizures in the ICU: a retrospective database study</h3>
<ul>
<li>
<p>DOI: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10072-021-05305-z">10.1007/s10072-021-05305-z</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>代码地址：<a href="https://github.com/shaou77/rdw_seizures">https://github.com/shaou77/rdw_seizures</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>太太发得比我好系列。人生第一个3区和＞3分的文章啊。但其实也是第一篇的延伸和模仿，赶在红细胞分布宽度的热度的尾巴上了。</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="paper4-development-and-validation-of-a-nomogram-for-predicting-atrial-fibrillation-in-patients-with-acute-heart-failure-admitted-to-the-icu-a-retrospective-cohort-study">Paper4 - Development and validation of a nomogram for predicting atrial fibrillation in patients with acute heart failure admitted to the ICU: a retrospective cohort study</h3>
<ul>
<li>
<p>DOI: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12872-022-02973-3">10.1186/S12872-022-02973-3</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>代码地址：<a href="https://github.com/shaou77/AFinAHF">https://github.com/shaou77/AFinAHF</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>理财成功系列（发的时候4区，第二年3区）。学习预测模型时的作品，中规中矩，一篇规范的预测模型文章该有的都有，不该有的也没有。</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="paper5-interpretable-machine-learning-models-for-predicting-90-day-death-in-patients-in-the-intensive-care-unit-with-epilepsy">Paper5 - Interpretable machine learning models for predicting 90-day death in patients in the intensive care unit with epilepsy</h3>
<ul>
<li>
<p>DOI: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.seizure.2023.11.017">10.1016/j.seizure.2023.11.017</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>代码地址：<a href="https://github.com/shaou77/rdw_seizures">https://github.com/shaou77/rdw_seizures</a> （没错，和paper3一个仓库，发表的时候忘记改仓库地址了，只好硬着头皮把它维护进去了）</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>参加了张敬信老师mlr3寒假学习班的作品。（感谢当时二区开区，很多课我都能按时上）学习机器学习的作品。模范了一篇也是使用mlr3的文章。从数据清洗，模型调参，模型比较，模型验证到模型解释的全套。不得不说，mlr3包确实强大。</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>太太发得比我好系列。3区，癫痫领域老牌期刊，epilepsy的预备役。</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>有GPT帮忙，代码已经简洁美观多了。</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="paper6-glycemic-comparison-index-gci-a-retrospective-analysis-of-its-prognostic-value-in-icu-patients-with-ami-and-diabetes">Paper6 - Glycemic Comparison Index (GCI): a retrospective analysis of its prognostic value in ICU patients with AMI and diabetes</h3>
<p>看到有一个一区期刊，分数9分多，糖尿病冠心病交叉领域，数据库文章也能发。我就冲着杂志主题做了一个研究，还是用我熟悉的数据库，花了一个春节假期的时间，做出了初稿。但是仍然被桌拒。然后投了几个糖尿病杂志，辗转一年，最终还是被老熟人，Springernature旗下的BMC系列接收了。</p>
<ul>
<li>DOI: [10.1186/s12902-025-01907-2] (https://doi.org/10.1186/s12902-025-01907-2)</li>
<li>代码库地址：<a href="https://github.com/shaou77/GCI">https://github.com/shaou77/GCI</a></li>
</ul>
<h3 id="paper7-real-world-efficacy-and-safety-of-perampanel-versus-levetiracetam-monotherapy-for-focal-epilepsy-a-single-center-retrospective-study">Paper7 -Real-world efficacy and safety of perampanel versus levetiracetam monotherapy for focal epilepsy: A single-center retrospective study</h3>
<p>终于有了一篇非数据库的文章，太太的横向课题，我做了所有的统计分析，撰写了结果和方法部分。代码不开源。<br>
*DOI:[10.1016/j.yebeh.2025.110630] (https://doi.org/10.1016/j.yebeh.2025.110630)</p>
<p>以后还有发表，本文将持续更新。（我巴不得月月更新）</p>
<h2 id="basic-information">Basic Information</h2>
<h3 id="cardiovascular-medicine-critical-care-since-2006">Cardiovascular Medicine - Critical Care (Since 2006)</h3>
<p>A hardworking  doctor born in the 80s, always working in a busy department.</p>
<p><strong>Github:</strong> <a href="https://github.com/shaou77" title="https://github.com/shaou77">github.com/shaou77</a>   |  <strong>Personal Blog:</strong> <a href="https://octocat.github.io">shaou77.github.io</a></p>
<h2 id="professional-skills">Professional Skills</h2>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>Cardiology Knowledge:</strong> Some accumulation, with a basic understanding of ECG, but the latest knowledge may be outdated.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Critical Care Knowledge:</strong> An amateur in this field with a shaky foundation. Respiratory and anti-infection areas are my weak points.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Editing Knowledge:</strong> Obtained a national intermediate-level publishing professional qualification at the age of 40. A bit of knowledge, but it's undeniable that during the early transition from a clinical doctor to a research-oriented doctor, the review work greatly benefited my thinking training.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Medical Research:</strong> Proficient in using other people's data for my research (so-called big data research). I have some experience with R and retrospective studies. In the AI era, I'm good at reproducing others' research (just lack original ideas), but reproduced studies are often hard to publish. (╯°Д°)╯︵┻━┻</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="research-experience">Research Experience</h2>
<h3 id="github-httpsgithubcomshaou77-2">GitHub - <a href="https://github.com/shaou77/">https://github.com/shaou77/</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>All my big data research based on public databases is available on my GitHub. After all, in the early stages of my career, the codes from experts on the platform were very helpful to me. I also do a little work to pass on my tiny sparks, although the quality is not high.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="paper1-association-between-red-cell-distribution-width-and-hospital-mortality-in-patients-with-sepsis-2">Paper1 - Association Between Red Cell Distribution Width and Hospital Mortality in Patients with Sepsis</h3>
<ul>
<li>
<p>DOI: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/03000605211004221">10.1177/03000605211004221</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Code:</strong> <a href="https://github.com/shaou77/rdw-and-sepsis">https://github.com/shaou77/rdw-and-sepsis</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>My first SCI, a breakthrough from 0 to 1. Initially, I was not very resilient and submitted to a few journals, got rejected, and finally submitted to one that was said to be easy to publish in. Ironically, it was fine when I submitted, but when it was published, it became a warning journal. You, a journal from Sage Publications older than me... It wasn't useful for my promotion, and the publication fee wasn't reimbursed. o(▼皿▼メ;)o</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>However, I think the quality of the article is okay. It was also my first paper to be cited double-digit times. Large sample size, comprehensive traditional statistical methods, detailed subgroup analysis, and even the then-fashionable NRI and IDI were done. I just didn't know how to use Rstudio's r or rmd files, so the code was saved in text, which might have some deviations.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Note: It is no longer a warning journal now.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="paper2-albumin-level-at-admission-to-the-intensive-care-unit-is-associated-with-prognosis-in-cardiac-arrest-patients-2">Paper2 - Albumin Level at Admission to the Intensive Care Unit Is Associated With Prognosis in Cardiac Arrest Patients</h3>
<ul>
<li>
<p>DOI: <a href="https://doi.org/10.7759/cureus.14501">10.7759/cureus.14501</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Code:</strong> None</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>It's actually an extension and imitation of the first paper. Back then, I was thin-skinned, got rejected a few times, and submitted to an E-SCI journal, which got published quickly. Surprisingly, it was useful for my promotion. Non-SCI, and I was too lazy to maintain the code.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="paper3-red-blood-cell-distribution-width-predicts-in-hospital-mortality-in-patients-with-a-primary-diagnosis-of-seizures-in-the-icu-a-retrospective-database-study-2">Paper3 - Red blood cell distribution width predicts in-hospital mortality in patients with a primary diagnosis of seizures in the ICU: a retrospective database study</h3>
<ul>
<li>
<p>DOI: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10072-021-05305-z">10.1007/s10072-021-05305-z</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Code:</strong> <a href="https://github.com/shaou77/rdw_seizures">https://github.com/shaou77/rdw_seizures</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>My wife published better than me series. My first paper in Q3 and with &gt;3 impact factor. But it's also an extension and imitation of the first paper, catching the tail end of the red cell distribution width trend.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="paper4-development-and-validation-of-a-nomogram-for-predicting-atrial-fibrillation-in-patients-with-acute-heart-failure-admitted-to-the-icu-a-retrospective-cohort-study-2">Paper4 - Development and validation of a nomogram for predicting atrial fibrillation in patients with acute heart failure admitted to the ICU: a retrospective cohort study</h3>
<ul>
<li>
<p>DOI: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12872-022-02973-3">10.1186/S12872-022-02973-3</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Code:</strong> <a href="https://github.com/shaou77/AFinAHF">https://github.com/shaou77/AFinAHF</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Successful financial management series (Q4 when published, Q3 the next year). A work while learning prediction models, standard and compliant, containing everything a standard prediction model article should have, and nothing it shouldn't.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="paper5-interpretable-machine-learning-models-for-predicting-90-day-death-in-patients-in-the-intensive-care-unit-with-epilepsy-2">Paper5 - Interpretable machine learning models for predicting 90-day death in patients in the intensive care unit with epilepsy</h3>
<ul>
<li>
<p>DOI: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.seizure.2023.11.017">10.1016/j.seizure.2023.11.017</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Code:</strong> <a href="https://github.com/shaou77/rdw_seizures">https://github.com/shaou77/rdw_seizures</a> (Yes, same repository as paper3, forgot to change the repository address when publishing, so I had to maintain it under pressure)</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>A product of Professor Zhang Jingxin's mlr3 winter course. (Thanks to the temporary ICU ward II, I could attend many classes on time) A work while learning machine learning. Modeled after an article also using mlr3. From data cleaning, model tuning, model comparison, model validation to model interpretation, a full set. I must say, the mlr3 package is indeed powerful.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>My wife published better than me series. Q3, an established journal in the field of epilepsy, a reserve for epilepsy.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="paper-6-glycemic-comparison-index-gci-a-retrospective-analysis-of-its-prognostic-value-in-icu-patients-with-ami-and-diabetes">Paper 6 - Glycemic Comparison Index (GCI): a retrospective analysis of its prognostic value in ICU patients with AMI and diabetes</h3>
<p>I came across a Q1 journal with an impact factor above 9 that focuses on the intersection of diabetes and coronary heart disease, and it also accepts database-based studies. Motivated by the journal’s scope, I designed this study using a database I was already familiar with. I spent the entire Spring Festival holiday completing the first draft. The manuscript was desk-rejected at first. I then submitted it to several diabetes-related journals, and after nearly a year of revisions and resubmissions, it was eventually accepted by the BMC series under Springer Nature, a journal family I know well.</p>
<ul>
<li>DOI: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12902-025-01907-2">10.1186/s12902-025-01907-2</a></li>
<li>Code repository: <a href="https://github.com/shaou77/GCI">https://github.com/shaou77/GCI</a></li>
</ul>
<h3 id="paper-7-real-world-efficacy-and-safety-of-perampanel-versus-levetiracetam-monotherapy-for-focal-epilepsy-a-single-center-retrospective-study">Paper 7 - Real-world efficacy and safety of perampanel versus levetiracetam monotherapy for focal epilepsy: A single-center retrospective study</h3>
<p>This is finally a study that does not rely on a public database. It originated from my wife’s horizontal research project. I was responsible for all statistical analyses and for writing the Methods and Results sections. The code for this study is not publicly released.</p>
<ul>
<li>DOI: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.yebeh.2025.110630">10.1016/j.yebeh.2025.110630</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[无题（一）]]></title>
        <id>https://shaou77.github.io/post/wu-ti-yi/</id>
        <link href="https://shaou77.github.io/post/wu-ti-yi/">
        </link>
        <updated>2024-05-29T05:02:10.000Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://shaou77.github.io/post-images/1716959384081.jpeg" alt="" loading="lazy"><br>
早上交班，周末病区来了两个心包积液的病人。<br>
突然想起我学心包穿刺的过程。心包穿刺是二级操作，在各种穿刺里危险度最大。我第一次做是升主治后，上级医生带着我在肿瘤科穿，穿了六七针都没有出来，满头大汗…若干次后，我去他科会诊，不用助手，独自一人，随手就把心包穿刺给做了。当时，能独立做心包穿刺的医生，还是有点少。</p>
<blockquote>
<h2 id="可是时代变了">可是，时代变了</h2>
</blockquote>
<p>超声越来越普及，超声下穿刺的技术也越来越成熟。超声下心包穿刺的难度较传统降低，安全性也大大增加。<br>
我也设想过，退休后有时间，去学学国画。从这一年AI的进化来看，自己画似乎意义也不大了。<br>
站在新时代的大门，马车夫不去学驾驶的话，那么就会被抛弃。</p>
<hr>
<p>In the Morning Handover, Two Patients with Pericardial Effusion Were Admitted to the Ward over the Weekend</p>
<p>Suddenly, I recalled my experience of learning pericardiocentesis. Pericardiocentesis is a second-level procedure and is the most dangerous among various punctures. The first time I performed it was after I became an attending physician, with a senior doctor guiding me in the oncology department. After six or seven attempts without success, I was sweating profusely... After several attempts, I went to another department for a consultation, and without an assistant, I performed the pericardiocentesis alone with ease. At that time, there were still quite a few doctors who could perform pericardiocentesis independently.</p>
<blockquote>
<h2 id="however-times-have-changed">However, Times Have Changed</h2>
</blockquote>
<p>Ultrasound has become increasingly popular, and the technique of ultrasound-guided puncture has become more refined. The difficulty of ultrasound-guided pericardiocentesis is much lower than the traditional method, and the safety has greatly increased.<br>
I also thought that after retirement, I would have time to learn Chinese painting. But seeing the evolution of AI this year, it seems that drawing by oneself is not very meaningful anymore.<br>
Standing at the gate of the new era, if a coachman doesn't learn to drive, he will be left behind.</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[什么是惆怅]]></title>
        <id>https://shaou77.github.io/post/shi-me-shi-chou-chang/</id>
        <link href="https://shaou77.github.io/post/shi-me-shi-chou-chang/">
        </link>
        <updated>2024-05-27T16:17:11.000Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://shaou77.github.io/post-images/1716827464630.png" alt="" loading="lazy"><br>
夜里面突然梦到一个中学时的好朋友（男），很久都不曾想起过。醒来后独面黑夜，年轻时的共同回忆从脑海中喷涌而出。清晨打开微信，搜索到他的名字，没有聊天记录，没有朋友圈，想打点什么，又不知道打点什么。</p>
<hr>
<p>In the middle of the night, I suddenly dreamed of a good friend from middle school (male), someone I hadn't thought of in a long time. Waking up to face the dark night alone, memories of our youth together surged in my mind. In the morning, I opened WeChat, searched for his name, and found no chat history, no Moments. I wanted to send him a message, but didn't know what to say.</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[乡情]]></title>
        <id>https://shaou77.github.io/post/xiang-qing/</id>
        <link href="https://shaou77.github.io/post/xiang-qing/">
        </link>
        <updated>2024-05-17T04:40:27.000Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure data-type="image" tabindex="1"><img src="https://shaou77.github.io/post-images/1716827384891.jpg" alt="" loading="lazy"></figure>
<h3 id="今天在病房里听到了家乡话">今天在病房里听到了家乡话</h3>
<p>一个80多岁的株洲老爷爷，南下广东已近40年。三个月前得了脑梗，现在遗留严重的认知障碍，智能减退，无法交流。早上查房的时候他一直喃喃自语，讲的就是亲切的株洲话（约等于长沙话）。<br>
不知道那些叶落异国的游子们，最后闪过的念头是不是也是在用家乡话。</p>
<p><strong>PS</strong>：2022年秋天首发朋友圈，现在在新博客上存个档。最后一段，当时想的是我的伯伯，年轻出国，海外70多年。但每次在长沙见他，还能讲口流利的长沙话。最后90多岁，在COVID-19大流行时，叶落美国东海岸。</p>
<p>#老文新发</p>
<h3 id="heard-my-hometown-dialect-in-the-ward-today">Heard My Hometown Dialect in the Ward Today</h3>
<p>An 80-year-old grandpa from Zhuzhou, who moved to Guangdong nearly 40 years ago. Three months ago, he suffered a stroke and now has severe cognitive impairment, diminished intelligence, and is unable to communicate. During the morning rounds, he kept muttering in his familiar Zhuzhou dialect (which is roughly the same as Changsha dialect).</p>
<p>I wonder if those who drift far from home, in their final moments, also have thoughts in their hometown dialect.</p>
<p><strong>PS</strong>: Originally posted on WeChat Moments in autumn 2022, now archived on my new blog. In the last paragraph, I was thinking of my uncle, who went abroad when he was young and spent over 70 years overseas. But every time we met in Changsha, he could still speak fluent Changsha dialect. He finally passed away in his 90s on the East Coast of the United States during the COVID-19 pandemic.</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[缘起]]></title>
        <id>https://shaou77.github.io/post/yuan-qi/</id>
        <link href="https://shaou77.github.io/post/yuan-qi/">
        </link>
        <updated>2024-05-13T03:54:14.000Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>荒废了多年之后，又重新开始写博客。只是为了一个契机。</p>
<p>前天在和欢欢小朋友聊天，说起过苦日子的事。突然想起我外婆。她和说过，在她少女时候，正值抗日战争，国军军队行军经过她家，把家里用来喂猪的猪潲都吃光了。当时在湖南的战局确实焦灼了很久。白云苍狗，一晃已经过去了近百年，当时经过外婆家的那些士兵，不知道有几个人能平安的回家，有几个人又去了台湾。现在，外婆也过世10多年了，若干年后这段记忆碎片，将无人得知。</p>
<p>我想，我脑袋里有时候有一点点火花，所以应该记录下来。在大学时我开通过新浪博客，只是现在都访问困难。我写过一段时间的QQ空间，但是访问有权限。想来想去，还是自己搭建一个博客网站吧，我也是一个不怕折腾的人。GitHub是开源软件的大本营，应该持续的时间会比较久，网址就用它了。至于后人有没有兴趣，我就不管它了。毕竟现时代的一切最终都会湮灭。</p>
<p>今年我目前过得不是很顺利，去年投的一篇文章，被拒了多次，现在还在外审，专家还没有接。今年年初信心满满写了一篇文章，被目标期刊秒拒，现在转投在一个3区杂志，一个月了，连编辑还没有找到。普通话考了两次，第一次差2分就过了，第二次成绩反而降了一截。不管什么语言，发音确实是我的软肋，提升还不知从何着手。写写东西，或许能保持一下内心的平静吧。</p>
<hr>
<h1 id="origin">Origin</h1>
<p>After neglecting it for many years, I have decided to start blogging again. All it took was a simple conversation.</p>
<p>A few days ago, I was chatting with my daughter about tough times. Suddenly, I remembered my grandmother. She once told me that during her childhood, amidst the Second Sino-Japanese War, the Nationalist soldiers passing by her house ate all the pig slop. Indeed, the battle in Hunan was intense and prolonged. It's been nearly a century since then. I wonder how many of those soldiers made it home safely and how many ended up in Taiwan. My grandmother has been gone for over ten years now, and in a few more years, these memories will fade into oblivion.</p>
<p>So, I thought I should record the occasional sparks that light up in my mind. In college, I had a blog on Sina, but now it's hard to access. I also wrote on QQ Space for a while, but access was restricted. It seems better to set up my own blog. GitHub, being a hub for open-source software, might last longer. Whether future generations are interested or not, I don't mind. Ultimately, everything will fade away.</p>
<p>This year hasn't been very smooth. An article I submitted last year has been rejected multiple times and is still under review, with no experts taking it up. This year, I wrote another article with high hopes, but it was instantly rejected by the target journal. It's now with a Q3 journal for a month, and the editor hasn't even been assigned yet. I took the Mandarin proficiency test twice; the first time I almost passed, but the second time my score dropped. Pronunciation is indeed my weakness, and I don't know where to start. Writing might help keep my mind at peace.</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
</feed>